<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A convocation speech, by Mr. Thomas Warmstry, one of the clerks for the Diocesse of Worcester: against images, altars, crosses, the new canons, and the oath, &amp;c.</title>
            <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97168</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W882</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E199_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14000</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859593</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859593</idno>
            <idno type="VID">157521</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97168)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 157521)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 35:E199[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A convocation speech, by Mr. Thomas Warmstry, one of the clerks for the Diocesse of Worcester: against images, altars, crosses, the new canons, and the oath, &amp;c.</title>
                  <author>Warmstry, Thomas, 1610-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Idols and images --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Speeches, addresses, etc., English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:157521:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:157521:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A CONVOCATION SPEECH, BY M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>THOMAS WARMSTRY,</hi> one of the Clerks for the Dioceſſe of WORCESTER: <hi>AGAINST</hi> Images, Altars, Croſſes, the new Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and the Oath, &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Monander.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the yeare, 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:157521:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:157521:2"/>
            <head>A CONVOCATION SPEECH, BY Mr. <hi>THOMAS WARMSTRY,</hi> one of the Clerks for the Dioceſſe of WORCESTER. <hi>AGAINST</hi> Images, Altars, Croſſes, the new Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and the Oath, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Am not unſenſible how farre more unfit it is for me to ſpeak in ſo grave and reverend an Aſſembly, than for many others, whoſe riper yeares and more mature ſtudies have furniſhed them with farre greater abilities. But ſince it hath pleaſed the Clergy to make choice of me for their Servant, I crave leave to diſcharge my conſcience.</p>
            <p>Wee cannot be ignorant of the rumours that are abroad, the great exceptions that are taken againſt the late Canons, the great and generall accuſations that are laid upon the late Synod, for the making and contriving of them. And it is ſtrange, me thinks, when every body talks of it, that we our ſelves ſhould be ſilent,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:157521:3"/>whom it moſt concernes. It will be ſmall credit to the Church, that others muſt be faine to correct thoſe errors that we have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted. It cannot be, I conceive, either piety or wiſedome in us to deſert the cauſe. If we be juſtly charged, we are engaged to a redreſſe; every man is bound to fill up the pit which he himſelfe hath digged. If unjuſtly, we have a tie upon us to uſe our endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to remove the ſcandall, and ſlander. It muſt needs lie upon us either to make good that we have done, or to amend that which we have miſdone: leſt to the reſt this blemiſh alſo be laid upon us, that we are buſie, when there is nothing to doe; and altogether remiſſe when wee have moſt work; or that we have hands to wound, but none to cure. I ſhould bee glad that our buſineſſe were for Iuſtification; but I feare there is ſomething elſe to bee done. For mine owne part, it is not unknowne, I beleeve, unto many that are here preſent, that I was againſt many things in the ſaid Canons, in the agitation of them in the laſt Synod; and particularly againſt the Oath. And as I oppoſed it then; ſo I continue ſtill in my diſſent from it: Not that I diſlike any thing that the Oath intends principally to guard. I diſrelliſh neither the Doctrine, nor the Diſcipline, nor the Government of the Church. Not the Doctrine, I embrace it hearily; and I conceive the Church of <hi>England</hi> may be herein the patterne of the world: and that if ever any Church hath taken that living water clearly and purely from the fountaine, it is the Church of <hi>England.</hi> Not the Diſcipline, I entertaine it willingly, ſo farre as it is eſtabliſhed by law: I wiſh indeed there might bee no private Innovations. I love outward reverence in Gods worſhip, ſo that it be directed to the right object; not to Altars, not to Images; but to God. I love all Ceremonies that truly tend thereunto, or to decency, or to uniformity, which I acknowledge to be moſt neceſſary in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious actions. But I deſire that in affectation of reverence wee breed no contempt; that in contrivance of decency, we bring in no blemiſhes: That the Church may not ſeeme to bee infected with the humours of ſome women in this age, that never think themſelves handſomly dreſt, but when they are in ſome new and fantaſticall faſhion: That while we endeavour Vniformity, wee doe not multiply diviſion. We may be ſo buſie in drawing the two ends together, that we may break the ſtaffe in the midſt.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:157521:3"/>That wee bee not ſo carefull to preſerve Vniformity with others that are without, that wee make diſſentions within our owne Church. The truth is, I wiſh there might be nothing ſcandalous, nothing frivolous in the Church. Nothing ſcandalous, not ſo much as a title. Though I love the ſacrifice of Almes, and Praiſe, and I hope ſhould not refuſe my ſelfe to be a ſacrifice unto God, though a burnt one; yet I know no need of any materiall Altar: becauſe I know no materiall Sacrifice, but that eternall Sacrifice of Chriſt upon the Croſſe. And though it may be urged, That the Primitive Church uſed the name of Altar for the holy Table, yet that makes it neither neceſſary nor warrantable for us to doe the like; unleſſe together with the language we could call back the purity, the ſimplicity of the Primitive times. Now things are ill interpreted, it concernes us to be more cautelous; leſt if not now, yet in after ages our language may be urged for the confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Hereſie, when it cannot be anſwered for us; as we may anſwer for the Primitive times, That the Hereſies were not then broacht, and therefore the ſpeech more looſe. It is a dangerous thing to give an Hereſie the advantage of a Metaphor, which the Devill wants not skill in time to reduce back unto the killing letter. Beſides, the language of the Scripture and the Apoſtles is the moſt pare and the moſt ancient language of the Primitive Church; and we read of no Altar there after Chriſt, but the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar of the Croſſe, or of Chriſt crucified. I deſire there may bee nothing ſcandalous: I wiſh the true Image of God in Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and true Holineſſe may be reſtored in the ſpirituall Temples of our ſoules But I deſire, at leaſt an abatement in the number, and limitation, for the manner and ſituation of Images in the mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Churches becauſe I doubt they are ſeandalous to all ſorts.</p>
            <p>To our Selves; to the ſtrongeſt in one ſenſe, it laies a ſcandall upon many of them, brings them into ſuſpition of inclination to Popery. And this ſuſpition i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the poyſon of the Church, and ought by all meanes to be avoided. To the weak; who are drawn hereby into a jealory of our Church, and moved toward a ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And ſurely it is no policy; nor can be a thing acceptable to Almighty God, to fill the Church with congregations of dead Images and Saints, and to empty it of the living Images of God. <hi>The dead praiſe not thee, O Lord,</hi> ſaith the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 115.17.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:157521:4"/>
               <hi>Hee is the God of the living, and not of the dead,</hi> ſaith our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour.</p>
            <p>Scandalous to the Papiſt. Alas, it will never win them: can you think them ſuch children as to be allured with a Baby? it may confirm and ſtrengthen them; and I doubt not but the Devill hath skill enough to perſwade them from hence, that they need not come over to us; for we are drawing, as faſt as we can, to them. And we know not what uſe our Poſterity may make of thoſe Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues and Images, which we have ſet up. I am ſure they are <hi>paratura Idololatriae:</hi> and you had beſt take heed how you lay rats-bane in your childrens way, and how you ſtrengthen the hands of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Scandalous to the Iew. The materiall Croſſes in our Churches may be, I doubt, a block in their way, as well as the Croſſe of Chriſt: they have wretchedly taken this, let us not give them that. This God, I hope, will remove by illumination, and it may be hoped, the time drawes neere: O let not us be hinderers of ſo great, ſo glorious, ſo deſireable a work, by laying a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Images in their way. <hi>Cypriane de valera,</hi> a learned Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard, in his Preface unto thoſe two Treatiſes which he hath written againſt the Supremacy of the Pope, and againſt the Maſſe, telleth us of one <hi>Paulus Pricius</hi> a learned Hebrew, that turned Chriſtian in <hi>Pavia,</hi> who complained of this, and deſired a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of it, ſaying, That it was very requiſite, that Images ſhould be rid out of our Churches; for that they were the cauſe that kept many Iewes from embracing Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Scandalous to the Turk, and to the Heathen alſo. It may be a meanes to make the Heathen like his ſuperſtition the better, with which we doe ſo dangerouſly comply, at leaſt in outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; and to confirme and promote the Turk in his abhorring of the profeſſion of Chriſtianity. It is the judgement of that learned Spaniard I before named: <hi>Muchos Moros, Turcos, y Indios ſe converti jan a Chriſto, ſi non fuere Por la offenſa, y eſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalo de las Imagines,</hi> many Moors, Turks, and Indians might be converted to Chriſtianity, were it not for the ſcandall of Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery. Yee ſee then they doe much miſchiefe; though <hi>they have eyes and ſee not, mouthes and ſpeak not, hands and handle not, feet and walk not;</hi> yet they are not idle in our Churches, they have
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:157521:4"/>their dangerous and pernicious effects; and there is a ſtrong, though ſilent, diſſuaſiveneſſe in them to make many ſtand afarie off from Chriſt, and to abominate the ſervice of the Lord. But perhaps you will ſay, this is countervailed by ſome good that they bring with them. I muſt confeſſe it is juſt, that we ſhould conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der both, and lay aſwell the conveniences as the inconveniences in the ballance, that we may diſcover the true weight and value of things, and not cenſure them by the one, without the other: the want of which moderation in our judgements hath cauſed great commotions and tumults in the Church. Let us then ſee wherein they profit Gods people.</p>
            <p>If they doe any good in the ſervice of God, they are profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>aut diſcentibus, aut docentibus, aut or antibus, aut communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cantibus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Hemmingius:</hi> or (let me adde) <hi>eleemoſynam dantibus;</hi> for unto theſe, I conceive, may be reduced all the holy and religious offices which God requires of us in his ſervice.</p>
            <p>Not to the Learners, it furthers them nothing. O yes, they are <hi>Idiotarum libri.</hi> Truly I doubt we have much to anſwer for it, that there are <hi>Idiotae in Chriſtianiſmo.</hi> Let us preach the word as we ought, and by Gods grace there will be no need, that there ſhould be either Images for Idiots, or Idiots for Images. This meanes of inſtruction is more ſafe, and more effectuall; this or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained by God, warranted by his Command, graced by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. That invented by men, without either Precept or Promiſe from God; but rather againſt both: and it can be no way accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to God, to exclude this to bring in that; to preach downe preaching to make way for Images. It is a notable obſervation, and, I doubt, may rub upon our times, that <hi>Hemmingius,</hi> and <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> have in this point: That when the Miniſters of the Church began to give themſelves to idleneſſe, and ſilence in the Church, then began the frequent uſe of Images in Gods houſe. They were built up, it ſeemes, upon the ruine of Gods Ordinance; as if the Church-men, to excuſe and countenance their own floth and negligence, had ſet up ſtocks and ſtones to be their Curats, and to take their turnes in the inſtruction of the people. And ſo the Prieſts became, as it were, dumbe Idols; and the Idols were made dumbe Prieſts to doe their office in Gods ſervice. And ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly it fals out unhappily in our time; to this purpoſe, wherin prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:157521:5"/>of the word is diſcountenanced, and left off; and in ſtead thereof, as it were, Pictures brought in. And I pray you conſider whether the Authors of the one were not thoſe that are guilty of the other. But alas, how unſafe is it for us to commit our charges to ſuch Inſtructors! ſince the Prophets tell us, <hi>they are teachers of lies, of vanity, and falſſhood, Habak.</hi> 2.18. <hi>Ierem.</hi> 10.8, 14. Beſides, if any bee ſo ſtupid as, as that they cannot be inſtructed without an Image, it may be feared, they will be ſo ſtupid too, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to miſtake the true uſe of an Image, if there be any ſuch in the Church.</p>
            <p>And as little helpfull are they to Preachers. They can neither inſpire, nor enlighten, nor inflame their hearts with holy zeal in the preaching of the word, nor open unto them a doore of ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terance; for how ſhould they open his mouth, ſince they cannot their owne? And they have <hi>rem anguſtam demi,</hi> that muſt ſeek unto them for matter to furniſh out their Sermons; neither are they able to furniſh them with any excellent ſtuffe, unleſſe they would make uſe of them for the art of memory, which I doubt would prove but of little availe to them. And if I miſtake not, windowes and pillars may ſerve as well.</p>
            <p>But what? are they behovefull to men in their Prayers, and divine worſhip? They may be robbers of God indeed herein, and ſo make the houſe of Prayer a den of theeves, but for any fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therance of theſe Duties unto him there is none at all, but rather much hinderance. There are but two parts of our worſhip and ſervice in this kinde, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the internall worſhip of the ſoule, which conſiſts in inward devotion; and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the externall of the body, conſiſting for the moſt part in out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Reverence. Now for the firſt, they further us not in our devotion; for that is uſually the more intended, by how much the minde is more fixed unto God, and hath a more free paſſage unto him: whereas theſe ſerve rather to diſtract the minde, and are as blocks and hinderances in the thoughts paſſage unto God; eſpecially being ſet up in the very faces of Oratories, as if they were placed there to intercept our Prayers, and to way-lay our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions between the ſoule and heaven. And for outward Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, I ſpeak it confidently, I beleeve they have been a great meanes to make men abhorre it in the houſe of God, leſt they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:157521:5"/>ſhould bee entrapped thereby unto Idolatry; or at leaſt bee thought to give it to Altars, or Images, which are ſet up (as is doubted) of purpoſe before them. <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare the Chriſtians to Idolatry, or at leaſt to draw them into the imputation of it, ſet up his Idols upon his owne Picture; that if they bowed, and gave civill reſpect (as was accuſtomed it ſeems) to the repreſentation of the Emperour, they might then be taken to be worſhippers of the Heathen Idols: if they refuſed, they were executed, not as Chriſtians, but as deſpiſers of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his reſemblance. And truly the caſe is very like with Chriſtians now in reſpect of theſe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,<note place="margin">As thoſe wicked Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutors of which Ruffinus <hi>lib. 1. cap. 7.</hi> who ſet up the Image of <hi>Venus</hi> in the place where our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour was crucified; that if any ſhould come thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to worſhip our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, they might bee thought to worſhip that Idol, &amp;c. <hi>Et ob hoc in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frequens &amp; penè oblivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oni datus fuerat locus, ſaith</hi> Ruffin.</note> being ſet up in place of Gods wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; if they doe outward reverence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, they are in danger to be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>interpreted to doe it to the Altars, and Images; if they refuſe to doe it unto them, they are accuſed, and puniſhed, as denying it to God; and ſo they are in a manner neceſſitated to appeare ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prophane, or ſuperſtitious, and idolatrous.</p>
            <p>Neither doe they any way further men in the uſe of the Sacrament. Wee know the eyes of the body and ſoule have both their full work there; and therefore ſhould be ſequeſtred as much as may be from other objects, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, at that moſt dreadfull time, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> calleth it. The eye of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is there to be fixed upon the repreſentation of Chriſt and his ſufferings, and benefits, which himſelfe hath ſet before us in the holy Sacraments, and is not to bediſtracted by any other Images, whether Crucifixes, or other, ſet up, as it were, to outface them, which ſeeme to lay a ſecret imputation of imperfection and inſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiency upon that bleſſed Ordinance of Chriſt, as if that were not enough without a Crucifix, or as if the painter or carver had ſet forth the paſſion in the Picture, better than Chriſt in the holy Supper. And for the eye of the ſoule, that is to be fixed on Chriſt himſelfe, his bitter ſufferings, and thoſe glorious bleſſings thereby
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:157521:6"/>imparted unto us, and not to be taken up with any humane ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifices; the ſplendor whereof may ſteale away the ſoule from its attention to this holy buſineſſe, and ſo deprive it of the comforts of the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Almes-deeds,</hi> Though the Prieſts of <hi>Rome</hi> finde (I doubt not) good commings in by this meanes, and receive good Rent for their Tenant-Images, for the houſe-roome they allow them in their Churches; yet they are not like to be beneficiall to the poore: Yea, the fruitleſſe charge and coſt which is beſtowed upon them in their framing, adorning, and offerings, is a great meanes both to diſable and diſcourage Gods people, for enlarging their hearts, or at leaſt their hands to the poore. Indeed theſe Images, though they have no mouthes to ſpeak, yet they have, as it were, mouthes to devoure the bread of the hungry: and the coſtly attire of theſe dead Images is paid for dearly, it may bee feared, by many poore living Images of Chriſt, that by this means are faine to goe naked to the ſhame of Chriſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>And if we adde unto this the dangerous oppoſition that is in the uſe of them in Gods worſhip, unto the rules and lawes of God himſelfe; whereby they are not only ſcandalous but impious, thwarting the rule not only of charity, but of faith too; as may appeare by the ſecond Commandement, and alſo by many other places in holy Writ, wherein this practice is vehemently oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and condemned.<note place="margin">Concil. Elibert. can. <hi>36.</hi> Placuit Pictu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras in Eccleſia eſſe non debere, ne qnod colitur, aut adoratur, in parietibus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pingatur. Vide Athanaſ. contra Idol. Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>113.</hi> Chryſoſt. in Geneſ. Hom. &amp; ad Philippenſ. <hi>1.3.</hi> Hom. <hi>11.</hi> Theodor. in Pſal. <hi>113.</hi> Iuſtin. Mart. in dialog. cum Tryphon. Clem. Alex. Strom. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; in Paraen. Tertul. de idolat. c. <hi>3.4.5.</hi> Cyprian de Valera, in the Preface of his Dos Tratados del Papay de la miſſa. Lamprid. in Alex. Sever. vide drelin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>court Triomphe de l'egliſe part. <hi>2.1.26.</hi> art. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And the contrariety that it hath both to the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice of the Primitive Church (which in other matters we talk much of) judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, being abſolutely and clearly forbidden by that ancient Eliberian Councell celebrated in <hi>Spaine</hi> in the yeare 305. as <hi>Binius</hi> computes; and extremely diſliked by the ancient Fathers of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:157521:6"/>the Church, as <hi>Origen, Iuſtin Martyr, Tertullian, Athanaſius, Epiphanius, &amp;c.</hi> inſomuch that they proceeded ſo farre ſome of them, it ſeemes, as to condemne the very art of painting and carving, as deceitfull and miſchievous, and as brought into the world by the Devill himſelfe: And Practice alſo, ſutable to their judgement, in that they were not in uſe among them in Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as learned <hi>Drelincourt</hi> obſerves to be acknowledged by divers of the Popiſh authors themſelves, as <hi>Libius, Gregorius, Gyraldus de Dits Gentium, Syntagm.</hi> 1. <hi>Georg. Caſſander Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult. art.</hi> 21. and as may be ſeen, if we look but upon the deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Temples of <hi>Adrian,</hi> hereby noted to have been di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed from the Heatheniſh Temples, and of the Temples of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> the magnificence and ornaments whereof are deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed in Eccleſiaſticall hiſtory (as is obſerved by a learned French writer) without the leaſt mention of Pictures, or Images: yea it was the reproach (as one noteth) that the Heathens laid upon the Chriſtians in the ancient times, That they had neither Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, nor Altars, nor Images.<note place="margin">Vide Orig. contra Celſ. lib. <hi>6.7.</hi> Minut. in Octav. Lactant. div. Inſtit. lib. <hi>2.</hi> Clem. Alex. Strom. <hi>5.6.</hi> Iren. adverſ. Haereſes lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>23.24.</hi> Epiphan. lib. <hi>1.</hi> Haereſ. <hi>27.</hi> Auguſt de Haereſ. cap. <hi>7.</hi> Pet. Crinit. lib. <hi>9.</hi> de honeſta diſciplina.</note> And if we note (as one noteth) that they were not uſed in thoſe times but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famous Hereticks; and that there have beene Lawes made againſt them by publick authority in thoſe times; as that Law of <hi>Valens</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius, &amp;c.</hi> if, I ſay, we adde theſe things, That they are contrary to the Word of God, to the judgement and practice of the Primitive Church, have not been anciently uſed but by wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Hereticks, and laſtly have been openly cried downe by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, we ſhall finde, I beleeve, little ground to make ſo much of them in the Church, as ſome have done.</p>
            <p>But what then? muſt we demoliſh theſe Churches, that are decked and adorned with Images? There is no need of that I hope. There are many things now to be reformed, that I hope will not be pulled downe: And yet if there were ſuch need, I dare ſay, better fortie Churches demoliſht than one Soule ruined, ſince a Soule is the purchaſe of Chriſts blood; ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teriall
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:157521:7"/>Churches not ſo. Theſe Scandalls I deſire may bee removed.</p>
            <p>And as I deſire there may bee nothing ſcandalous in the Church, ſo that there may be nothing frivolous, or irrationall, that our ſervice may be a reaſonable ſervice. I know not why we ſhould have can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dles in the day time.<note place="margin">Concil. Eliber. cap. <hi>34.</hi> &amp; Lactant. div. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit. lib. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi> Accendunt lumina velut in tenebris agenti. — Si coeleſte lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men quod dicimus ſolem, contemplari ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lint, jam ſentiant quod non indigeat lucer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis eorum Deus. — Num igitur men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis ſuae compos putandus eſt, qui autori &amp; datori luminis candelarum &amp; cerarum lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men offert pro munere? Aliud verò ille à nobis exigit lumen, &amp; quidem non fumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, ſed (ut ait Poeta) liquidum, atque clarum, mentis ſcilicet, quod exhibere non poteſt, niſi qui Deum agnoverit. — Haec eſt religio coeleſtis, non quae conſtat ex rebus corruptis, ſed virtutibus animi, qui oritur è coelo. Hic verus cultus eſt in quo mens colentis ſeipſam Deo immaculatam victi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam ſiſtit.</note> I wiſh there may not be ſo much as an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of a fruitleſſe Prelacy, or Clergy in the Church, that only fill the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, but give no light. I love orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Church, ſo that they be not toyiſh or theatricall. I hold it very fit that God as he is the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of our riches, ſo he ſhould be ſerved with them. But I wiſh that may not befall our times that <hi>Aegidius Viterbienſis</hi> noteth to have befallen the times of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine; Conſtantini tempora</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ut ſacris rebus multum adjecere decoris, &amp; ornamenti, ita morum vitaeque ſeveritatem non parum enervârunt. Verus ornatus Templorum utilis &amp; Deo gratus</hi> (ſaith <hi>Hemmingius) eſt concio, cantio, oratio, &amp; commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio, &amp; non quae haec impediunt &amp; vitiant.</hi> Yea an holy congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is the beſt furniture of the Church. I wiſh our ſpeciall care may be for this, and then let the outward adornation, as farre as grave and decent, not be neglected. The truth is, I can beare much in the Church, rather than diſturbe the peace, or reſiſt the Government: which gives me occaſion to ſpeak of the laſt thing mentioned in the Oath, The Government of the Church.</p>
            <p>And for this I doe acknowledge my ſelfe bound by the law of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:157521:7"/>God to beare great reſpect to this Ordinance of God, whereſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever I finde it, I am to eſteem it as a pretious ſtone, though I finde it in a dunghill of vices. But where it is ſet in gold, found aſſocia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with vertue and holineſſe, there indeed it is exceeding glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, and may challenge a double reſpect: but howſoever it is due to Gods Subſtitute, whatſoever the man may be in his owne perſon, and that in point of conſcience: and this duty doth conſiſt chiefly in three things; <hi>Honour, Obedience,</hi> and <hi>Subjection.</hi> I am to honour them in my thoughts, in my words, in my actions, yea with my eſtate too, if there be ability in me and exigence in them. To obey them in all juſt commands whatſoever, whereſoever, either in the commands themſelves, or in the acts which they en<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyne me, ſo they are not contrary to Gods law; for I know the Governour may tranſgreſſe his duty in commanding, and yet my duty may tie me unto obedience. He offends, if he lay any tyrannous or frivolous bonds upon me, God will not have his people abridged of their liberty, without ſome reaſon or ground. And therfore all the commands of Governours, whether in Church or Common-wealth, ought to have their ground either in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, or Reaſon, and to be ſtreames from thoſe fountaines: they muſt depend upon the law of God either naturall or revealed; either as a confirmation thereof, or a declaration, or as a conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from theſe principles, or as a determination where his law hath appointed diverſe things to the ſame purpoſe and end, either abſolutely or diſ-junctively, either in the things themſelves, or in the end unto which they tend; they muſt finde an originall there, from whence they muſt be extracted, and coppied out, as it were. The law of God in Scripture and reaſon, is the maine and generall root and trunk, and all good lawes are branches that grow from thence; and whatſoever humane conſtitutions cannot either in a direct or collaterall line derive themſelves from them, are baſtard iſſues, and ſhamefull to their Parents; and the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maker ſinnes in framing of them. Yet the difficulty of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is to bee conſidered, and many things to be borne with, for though he have no ground in Gods law for his injunction, but it is meerly frivolous, and perhaps burthenſome; yet if his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority diſables him to make it, and it enjoyne me to no act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:157521:8"/>to mine allegiance unto God, it is his ſinne, but my afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and muſt be borne as other calamities; for though his law bath no good end, yet my obedience hath; obedience it ſelfe is a good and laudable thing; and I may have the end of maintaining order, or preſerving peace, and avoiding diſturbance in the Church or Common-wealth, of preventing ſcandall unto others and the like, which are ends preſcribed by Gods law to regulate and frame our actions by. All things are not to be turned upſide downe upon every inconvenience that may be apprehended in a law, whether it bee Eccleſiaſticall or Civill, For beſides that there are few that are fit Judges of a Law; That may be unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for the Governour to command, which yet is not unlawfull but expedient for me to obey, being commanded. As it was un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to command the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to make brick without ſtraw, as being tyrannous, and ſo ſinfull in him; but it was not unlawfull, but rather commendable in them to obey it, as farre as they could. And S. <hi>Paul</hi> will have ſervants to be obedient unto their Maſters, though they befroward and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe. Indeed if they doe enjoyne me to doe any thing wherein I ſhould offend againſt Gods lawes in the leaſt degree, no pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of any, though never ſo many or ſo great good ends, muſt make me withdraw my allegiance from him, and pay it to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane powers. The authority of all men is limited, and ſo muſt our obedience to them be alſo. The ſupreme power of God is the foundation of all authority; and therefore our duty unto that muſt be preferred in the firſt place, and without all leave or exception whatſoever. Peace muſt not be maintained with the ruines of Piety and Truſt. And any Scandall to my brother muſt rather be admitted, than I ſhould prevent it without Gods leave. The rule of Maſter <hi>Calvin</hi> is good here: <hi>Sicut libertas charitati, ita charitas fidei ſubjicienda eſt.</hi> Yet in this caſe I am to diſobey as modeſtly and offenſeleſly, and with as much ſhew of reverence to the Governour, as may ſtand with our duty unto God: yet reſolutely too, not faintly, or fearfully but as the three Children unto <hi>Nebuchadonezar, Dan.</hi> 9.15.17. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>And where we cannot yeeld obedience, we muſt yeeld the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:157521:8"/>third Duty of Subjection, eſpecially where the Authoritie is abſolute and ſupreme under God, which may be vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly ſtated according to the Lawes and Cuſtomes of ſeverall Countreyes and Dominions. Then in caſe we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not obey, we ought not to reſiſt but ſuffer; and yeeld a paſſive obedience where we may not yeeld an active one, according to the rule of Gods word: <hi>They that reſiſt ſhall receive unto themſelves damnation;</hi> and anſwerably to the practice of the Primitive Chriſtians, as we may ſee in that notable example of the Theban Legion, mentioned by <hi>Grotius de Iure Belli,</hi> out of <hi>Euſebius;</hi> who when they were commanded by <hi>Maximianus</hi> to worſhip his Idols, being Chriſtians, they conſtant'y denied to obey his command: but when he requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their lives, they ſubmitted without reſiſtance, though they were a ſtrong Legion of valiant ſouldiers.</p>
            <p>But I am yet in generals, and generals are clouds: more clearly and particularly therefore. I willingly ſubmit to the preſent Government of the Church in all parts ſpecified in the Oath by Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Archdeacons, and Deanes; and wiſh them ſo well, that I deſire they may never moulder away in corruptions, that may make them juſtly odious to the people, or bring any diſrepute upon them, that may bee deſtructive to their Eminencie. I envie not their Honours, but praiſe the bountie of Chriſtian Princes therein; yet I wiſh they may bee more glorious in holineſſe and pietie than in outward ſtate and dignity, That their honours may bee more adorned by them, than they by their honours; that the raies of their excelling vertues may even dimme and overcome the ſplend or of their outward ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and that they be above others more in goodneſſe, than in greatneſſe; and not ſo much affect the one, as to neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect the other; nor feed the one ſo much, as to ſtarve the other: <hi>nè filia devoret matrem, &amp; devoratà matre, devoret etiam ſeipſam:</hi> you may eaſily perceive there is ſome danger of it. I willingly ſubmit to their Authoritie, and wiſh it may bee ſo moderated by Piety and Charity, that it may be fatherly, not deſpoticall, much leſſe tytannicall; not as Lords over
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:157521:9"/>Gods heritage, but as Stewards of the manifold graces of God, that they may manage all things with Chriſtian com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſion, and puniſh others, when they muſt needs doe it, with ſuch hearts as are ready even to ſuffer with them in their cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, like a tender mother that will weep when ſhe is driven to chaſtiſe her child; like S. <hi>Paul,</hi> in whoſe language, (as a learned man obſerveth) to bewaile, and to correct, ſeemeth to have been all one, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.21. <hi>I feare,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that when I come againe, my God will humble me among you, and that I ſhall bewaile many that have ſinned already, and have not repented of their uncleanneſſe, and fornication, and laſciviouſneſſe, which they have committed.</hi> Surely, the cenſures of the Church, and Church-men, ſhould bee pronounced rather with teares, than fury, rather with ſighes, than ſupercilious frownes, that their love and pity to mens perſons may ſhine in the midſt of their greateſt ſeveritie, that they may ſee that they are armed, not againſt them, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their offenſes; and ſo, as much as may be, make their puniſhments lovely even to the ſufferers of them. I wiſh that they may weigh out the juſtice of Diſcipline, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection too with an equall hand, bending themſelves moſt againſt thoſe offences which are moſt againſt God, and not puniſh the weak and ſcrupulous (which hath more need of binding up than lancing, more need of Cordials, than Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſives) as the ſtubborne and perverſe: nor the omiſſion of an indifferent Ceremony, as the trampling upon the Law of God it ſelfe. Never let it be heard in our Iſrael, that the lawes and inventions of men, though harmeleſſe, though convenient, and wholeſome, are more valued than the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate lawes of God himſelfe. There is greater Scandall many times (it is doubt) in ſuch method and manner of puniſhing, than that is which they pretend to remove. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire that their Authoritie may be ſupported by thoſe pillars of Learning, Zeale, Holineſſe, Induſtrie, Meekneſſe, Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, and Humilitie: which may be like the ſeven pillars of the houſe of Wiſedome: which they ſhould be.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Learning,</hi> that they may bee ſhining Lights, to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:157521:9"/>illuſtrate the dark places of the earth.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Zeale,</hi> that they may be burning and ſhining Lights like <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt, to prepare the way of the Lord in mens Soules.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Holineſſe,</hi> that they may ſhine in their lives as well as in their doctrines; and their whole converſation may be a continuall viſible Sermon unto Gods people.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Induſtry,</hi> that their light be not hid <hi>ſub modio deſidiae,</hi> but that they may be like ſtarres in the firmament, as well of the bigger as of the leſſer magnitude, orderly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly fulfilling their courſes, and imparting their benigne aſpects unto one another, and their wholeſome influences unto the people in the Church; not forgetting thoſe maine and apoſtolicall works of prayer, and preaching the word, offering incenſe, and dreſſing the lamps, the moſt glorious part of their functions. Surely, howſoever ſome may miſtake it, a Biſhop is more ſplendid, and more like an Apoſtle in a Pulpit, than upon the Throne, as ſome ſtile it.</p>
            <p>Of <hi>Meekneſſe,</hi> that it may never be ſaid of them, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe when he was <hi>Saul,</hi> concerning zeale perſecuting the Church, That the fervour that is in them may be a gentle, not a ſcorching flame: not like the heat of a fever, to diſtemper and deſtroy; but like the naturall heat of the body to preſerve and nouriſh; that it may be a fire of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, not any immoderate fervour in them; and that it may be with them, as with God, that mercy may ſtill be more eminent than judgement, eſpecially in their owne cauſe. I wiſh they may remember that of <hi>Livia</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus, nihil glorioſius Principe impunè loeſo.</hi> It is a glory that ever de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to be conſpicuous amongſt us, that is ſaid to have been obſervable in Reverend <hi>Cranmer,</hi> noted to have been ſo meek in his owne injuries, that it grew almoſt into a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb of him, <hi>If any man will have the Archbiſhop to bee his friend, let him doe him an injury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Courage,</hi> that they be not ſo gentle as to deſert the cauſe of God in his Church.</p>
            <p>And of <hi>Humility</hi> the beſt baſis for greatneſſe to ſtand firme
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:157521:10"/>upon: that their eminency make them not ſupercilious, which is a ſigne indeed that men eſteeme themſelves, but uſually abates their eſteeme with others. <hi>Qui faſtum in ſublimitate caſtigat, docet ſe meruiſſe quod adeptus est,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee, I hope, that I am very well contented with the Doctrine, and Diſcipline, and Government of the Church. And yet notwithſtanding, as I have done, ſo I doe ſtill diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>approve of the late Oath. For though I approve of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; yet it may be doubtfull, whether it be fitly averred of any humane act abſolutely, That it containeth all things neceſſary to ſalvation; ſince it is the judgement of one of no ſmall note and eſteeme with many here (I beleeve,<note place="margin">L. of Canterb. against A. C. S. <hi>18.</hi> p. <hi>121.</hi>
               </note>) That before the queſtion may ſo much as be admitted, whether a thing containeth all things neceſſary to ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it muſt be granted to be of divine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, or to be the word of God. Though I diſlike not the Diſcipline, yet I hold it not unalterable; That were to fall into the errour of the Diſciplinarians, whom wee have hitherto oppoſed upon this very ground, That the Diſcipline of the Church may bee varied according to the varietie of times, perſons, and occaſions. Though I approve of the Government, yet I cannot hold it in all parts to be neceſſary; ſince I doubt not there were times, when the Church was well governed without ſome of them, which are clearly mentioned in the Oath. The truth is, I conceive the Oath unfit either to be taken or impoſed: I ſay either, becauſe I conceive they are two queſtions; Whether the Oath be fit to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed; Or being impoſed, whether it be fit to be taken.</p>
            <p>I hold it unfit to be taken, chiefly in foure reſpects.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. As ambiguous in ſome things.</item>
               <item>2. As hardly conſiſting with truth in others.</item>
               <item>3. As contradictory and deſtructive in the parts thereof unto one another.</item>
               <item>4. As tying us to that which may be inconvenient to the Church; if not now, yet in after times.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. As <hi>Ambiguous:</hi> whereas an Oath ought to be cleare,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:157521:10"/>being a bond of ſo ſtrict a nature, and ſo great a for feiture, That every man ought to be ſure of the tenour of the obligation ere he enter into it; ſince a mans whole eſtate of happineſſe both in preſent poſſeſſion, and in future hopes and expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, yea the ſoule it ſelfe, and that eternall inheritance wee look for in another world, is as it were tyed over for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance. Now this ſeemeth to be full of ambiguity.</p>
            <p>Ambiguous in the meaning and extent of the word <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine:</hi> ſince I take it, it is not ſo cleare, but it may be doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, whether that only is here meant, which is contained in the 39 Articles, or that alſo in the Homilies, the publick Catechiſme, and the Apology of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> and there hath been ſome controverſie of the Articles them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſome, or one of them; and others have been diverſly interpreted to ſerve the turnes of Arminians, and thoſe that have been diſ-affected to the true ſenſe of them.</p>
            <p>Ambiguous in the meaning and extent of the word <hi>Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline;</hi> whether it be to be underſtood only of that which is contained in the ordinary book of Canons in our Church, and the Rubrick in the Common prayer book; or whether of ſome other Rules before given in the time of King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth, or Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> or whether alſo of the Provincialls of <hi>Lindwood,</hi> and of the whole Canon lawes of the Popes, where they are not clearly revoked by Statute. From which dangerous uncertainties I wiſh the Church were delivered by a ſetled eſtabliſhment of ſome certaine Rules for the government thereof, agreeable to the word of God, and ſound reaſon: that we might not be faine to borrow from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to be go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by lawes borrowed from Antichriſt; though not An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſtian perhaps, as they are ſelected, and reſtrained here. Befides, there is doubt whether the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> be to be taken in the full extent of the word, or to be reſtrained only to the Government, as it ſeemes abuſively to bee reſtrained in the Oath; whereas in it ſelfe it is much larger than Government: and therefore to make that the <hi>exegeſis</hi> of <hi>Diſcipline</hi> may favour, I doubt, of Colluſion. And yet ſo it is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:157521:11"/>ſo cleare, what is here meant by Government; whether we ſweare to it only in reſpect of the Governours, or in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of all the Rules and exerciſe of Authority; which may be doubted; yea, was actually queſtioned and doubted of in the laſt Synod in the point of Excommunication by Lay-men. And if the Governours only are here meant, then there is doubt which and how many they are that are here meant. Eſpecially this Ambiguity is much encreaſed by the &amp;c. which I never remember to have been in the Oath, when it was read to us in the laſt Synod: neither am I alone in this forgetfulneſſe; but the like hath been affirmed by others alſo. How it crept in I know not, but I doe not beleeve, that ever before this, ſuch an obſcure addition found a roome in an Oath: neither doth it conſiſt with that clearneſſe which is required in that which is acknowledged to be <hi>ſtrictiſſimi Iuris.</hi> And though perhaps ſome of the larger ſiz'd conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences hold it unreaſonable, that we ſhould <hi>querelam offerre apicibus verborum;</hi> yet a good Chriſtian will be nice in the ſmalleſt point, where his ſalvation may any way be endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gered. And beſides, I learne from my Saviour, that one jot or tittle of his Word ſhall never paſſe away: <hi>obedientia in apicibus ſervanda eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Ambiguous alſo, it ſeemes, in the word <hi>[eſtabliſhed]</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that only is to be accounted eſtabliſhed, which is ſetled by knowne and publick Lawes, generally received in the whole Church; or that alſo which by the pretended autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie of ſome particular Governours, hath of late beene brought into the Church; ſince it runs not <hi>[as it ſtanas by Law eſtabliſhed]</hi> (as for my part, I thought it had done; and therefore my memory failes me thereto) but <hi>[as it ſtands eſtabliſhed]</hi> and no more; which in a large ſignification might perhaps tie us to divers Innovations, which have been brought in not without ſome ſhew of Authority.</p>
            <p>Ambiguous it is likewiſe in the word <hi>Conſent &amp;c.</hi> whether it tie only from yeelding a conſent to thoſe alterations which ſhall be made by others in Authoritie; or whether he may be ſaid to conſent which obeyes only, or he only that approves
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:157521:11"/>or admits of an alteration, having power to diſſent from it. If the former, then it would clearly contradict the Oath of Supremacy, yea of Allegiance too: which though I doe not ſo firmly beleeve (I confeſſe) becauſe I conceive a man may obey the alteration being made, and yet not be ſaid to conſent to alter; notwithſtanding this is not free from ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, and is too apt to be miſ-underſtood.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as it is thus full of Ambiguities, ſo I know not how in all points it will ſtand with Truth it ſelfe, where it is ſaid of the Government in the particulars named, <hi>viz. Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhops, Biſhops, Deanes and Archdeacons,</hi> with the unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable enlargement of an <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that of right it ought ſo to ſtand: the words are theſe; <hi>as it ſtands now eſt abliſhed, and as by right it ought to ſtand;</hi> which word <hi>[right]</hi> if it be equivocall, and to be underſtood either of Divine right, or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall, (as was anſwered in the laſt Synod) then wee ſhould admit of Equivocations in an Oath. But it ſeemes (if well conſidered) to imply a Divine right; for that clauſe <hi>[as it ſtands now eſtabliſhed,]</hi> if it be meant well, it muſt bee underſtood I conceive of that which is eſtabliſhed by Law, and that Law is the Eccleſiaſticall right whereby they ſtand. And therefore in That, after this it is further added, <hi>[and as byright it ought to ſtand]</hi> it ſeemes to averre that there is a further right than the Eccleſiaſticall Law it ſelfe, even a right which doth eſtabliſh the Law it ſelfe, whereby ſuch and ſuch Governours are appointed; and makes that, as it were, neceſſary in the Church; which I know not what right can doe, but a divine right: and this I am ſure ſome parts of the Government mentioned are altogether incapable of. Beſides, what the &amp;c. may include; <hi>nam quid non intus habet?</hi> for ought a mau certainly knowes, it may be <hi>Equus Trojanus,</hi> and many may lie hid there, that can pretend no more divine right to ſtand eſtabliſhed in the Church, than the &amp;c. it ſelfe to ſtand in the Oath.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as it is taxable of <hi>Ambiguity</hi> and <hi>Falſhood,</hi> ſo the Parts thereof ſeem to be contradictory and deſtructive to one another. Not to inſiſt long upon the diſſonancie and jarre
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:157521:12"/>that is between the Title and Preface with the Oath it ſelfe: In the Title it is. <hi>An Oath againſt all Innovations in Doctrine or Government.</hi> In the Preface it is, <hi>An Oath againſt all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations of Doctrine or Diſcipline.</hi> In the Oath it ſelfe it is neither againſt all Innovations, but only againſt ſome there intimated and expreſſed, nor againſt Innovations in Doctrine or Diſcipline, but with a limitation, or reſtraining <hi>Exegeſis, Diſcipline or Government.</hi> But let that paſſe. There ſeeme to be parts deſtructive to one another, even in the very Oath it ſelfe: the multitude of Ambiguities, and eſpecially the <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being not only equivocall, but alſo neceſſitating the Swearer (as may ſeem) to reſerve ſomething in his minde which is not expreſſed in the Oath. And yet in the later part of the Oath, he is to ſweare againſt all <hi>Equivocation</hi> or <hi>ſecret reſervation,</hi> whatſoever; which, how they can ſtand together, let any judge.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, it ſeemes to tye unto that which may be <hi>Inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient</hi> for the Church, every Clergy man may poſſibly bee a member of a Convocation or Synod; if ſo, then he is engaged to vote that which may be <hi>Convenient</hi> for the Church. Now in that the Government is not denyed to be alterable, it may ſo fall out that it may be requiſite to bring in ſome Alteration; and if ſo, then I ought not to tye my ſelfe from ever conſenting to an Alteration; leſt I thereby ſubject the Church unto ſuch bondage that may leave her remedileſſe to much miſchiefe hereafter. I ought not to lay any ſuch bond upon my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence as may bee againſt the performance of my duty, or the prevention, or redreſſe of miſchiefe among Gods people.</p>
            <p>Now in that it is unlawfull to be taken, as may appeare by the reaſons afore ſpoken of; then <hi>à majori</hi> it muſt needs be, it is unlawfull to be impoſed; ſo that if we have proved the former, we have proved both; for it is moſt clearely unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to enioyne that Oath which is not lawfull to bee taken. Beſides all this, it might bee added that there appeares not any need or neceſſity of this Oath; and <hi>Qui jurat ſine ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitate, peccat;</hi> an Oath being like to ſleeping or opiating Medicines, not to be adminiſtred but upon urgent exigencies.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:157521:12"/>Yea it proves to be oppoſite even to thoſe ends which it ſeems to aime at; it was never very likely to eſtabliſh, it hath, I doubt, ſhaken the preſent Government. <hi>Abundans cautela ſaepereddit ſuſpectos;</hi> unneceſſary caution leads to ſuſpition; and to tye with more bonds than needs to any thing, is many times to looſe the ſtrongeſt of all bonds, which is affection, and to encreaſe the hatred to it. <hi>Odimus quodcunque neceſſe eſt,</hi> is a Proverbe often made good: The old man in <hi>Arioſto</hi> may informe us of that, who having voluntarily contained himſelfe within the walls of <hi>Paris</hi> for ſome ſcores of yeares, being reſtrained at length by command, fell into ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiet deſires to ſee what was without the walls, that he went even out of the world for griefe.</p>
            <p>I might inſiſt upon the great and immoderate ſeverity in the Penalty propoſed to the refuſall of the Oath, being no leſſe than ſuſpenſion and deprivation: it may ſeeme a ſtrange kinde of Simonie to make a Benefice the price of periury; at leaſt, I am ſure, it cannot bee denyed, but that a man might bee unſatisfied in the ſenſe, and legality both of divers things in this Oath; though it were free from many things objected, and doe the office of a Miniſter faithfully as others, and beare a good Chriſtian heart toward God. And it is very hard to deprive ſuch of their offices and livings; which if it had taken effect, what miſchiefe might have come unto the Church by the loſſe of conſcionable Divines; and how many Clergy beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gars nught have beene turned abroad with their wives and children to the great ſcandall of the Church, I am glad wee are faine to gueſſe and imagine, and that it never came to bee knowne by a lamentable experience. For theſe reaſons as I have heretofore, ſo now againe, I declare my diſſent from the Oath.</p>
            <p>If my Subſcription bee urged, I was perſwaded that it was the practice of Councells and Synods, That the whole body ſhould ſubſcribe to thoſe Acts that are paſt by the maior part, as to Synodicall Acts, not withſtanding their private diſſent. If my Subſcription implied any more, I doe ſo farre recant and condemne it in my ſelfe, and deſire pardon both of God and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:157521:13"/>the Church, reſolving by Gods grace to be more cautelous hereafter.</p>
            <p>But is there no Balme in Gilead? are there no Phyſitians there? ſhall it be ſaid of us all as of <hi>Iobs</hi> friends, That weare all Phyſitians of no value? That it may not be ſaid of us, give me leave to conclude with two requeſts unto you, which I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to offer unto your grave Iudgements.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that wee may preferre a Petition to his Majeſty for power to review the late Canons and the Oath; that the wound of the Church may be cured by the Church.</p>
            <p>The ſecond, that as we have freedome of votes in the agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſo we may know our freedome in ſubſcription in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of our Synodicall Acts.</p>
            <p>So wee may have that happy ſtile to bee Repairers of the breaches in the walls of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and Re-edifiers of the houſe of God.</p>
            <p>And thus you have the thoughts of my heart, which I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you to judge of favourably; and if I have erred in any thing, to reduce mee meekly. And I could wiſh you had as cleare a diſſection of every mans minde here, as you have of mine.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
